[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Heat.
[Music]
Hello, good day and good evening
everybody wherever you are in the world
and welcome to the Ask a Bijit Show
episode 274. I hope everybody is doing
great. If you are a regular viewer,
thank you so much for being a regular
viewer and welcome back. If you are new,
do you're welcome. You're very welcome
over here. And let's see who is there on
the live chat with me. I can see Monty,
hello. I can see Aayush Singh. Hello
Sparti Uturi. Namaste. Sumit Patari Ato
Kumar. Aryan Patel. Bijesh SK Pinaka.
Uh Kanesh Koshik V Ramachandran Vant
Nikil Balyan Ashtoar Polar Bear Shrira
from Moscow. Nanita Badas
Priyanu vlog Shaker Roy Lakshai Shrihari
Arun Separ Krishna Giri Akash Jayant
Avin Chaitananya Manuja Dungar Singh
Johan a very very old-time viewer
welcome back sir Kushbu drawing and art
bat first Mishra Anupad
Satyam Kumar Chitan Aradya welcome back
sir Ashosh Kumar Vishahal Patra namask
Krish
Gupta Dhuv Durya Ram Shukla from Kpur.
Hello Satyam Kumar Vidhi Madar Hello
Shri Hari Arun again White Joe Abhishek
Shivastav Suchin Sharma Avin Dak
GK Hitan Shu Meta from Gujarat hello
Krishna Raunad from the Suryam
Netherlands hello satellite from Goa
Geopolit from Indor Pranipal from
Kolkata. Who else do we have? Rakkesh
Mist Mystri Mthun SP Abishek Shivasav
Mani Jangir
hello Makavin good evening Anurra Anir
God logistical roommate Viral Patel
knowledge with Malu Giga Chad is here
global affairs by SK Hitanchu Prasupati
Jooshi Hmed Kumar Gautami
and so many other people so good evening
good all of you and I'm going to take
questions from that I'm going to take
questions that you've asked in the
comments. Before we begin, before we
begin, people have been asking for a
long time that is there a way to
contribute to this channel without
becoming a member or something. So, how
about we change we change this logo to
this and you can contribute if you want
to. All right, why not? Let's do that.
Okay, with that said, let us uh get
going with the questions. A lot of
questions. Let's see how many I can take
in the next couple of hours. A lot
happening in the world. A lot of
questions about geopolitics. So let's
get going. Okay, this is a question not
about geopolitics but let's take it
quickly. Reddi says
this is by uh Tarun Reddi. Uh please
take this question. You're my guru for
my lifetime. Well, thank you so much. Uh
one day we'll meet you and well I would
be very happy to meet you sir. Um you
don't know how much impact you created
in my life. You literally changed my
life from my mindset to how to think and
how to see world. My worldview
completely changed because of you.
Learned everything in the past four
years. 21.
Well, thank you so much for the
beautiful words. I really appreciate
that. That's all I that's that's the
only objective of this to make people
see the world the way it actually is.
It's not a very nice place, but the
world has always been that way and
hopefully I'm doing something in that
direction. So, I'm very happy that it's
having some impact on on people and I
really appreciate your very kind words,
sir.
Okay. Amisha says, Amisha says Trump
talks of Pakistan's massive oil
reserves, but are they really there? And
Trump says that Pakistan may sell oil to
India.
Well, I discussed this in in some detail
yesterday in in yesterday's episode of
geostrategy.
Um geostrategy, we'll talk about that
later next week. Okay. So, uh yeah, I
spoke about this. Does Pakistan have
massive oil reserves? Pakistan may
perhaps be in the top 50 oil reserves
nations in the world by all reserves.
Possibly perhaps top 50 maybe slightly
out of top 50. I don't remember exactly
where the Pakistan's number is. You can
look it up. I'm not going to I'm not
going to look into that. But India has
way more oil reserves than Pakistan.
Right? But why does then Trump want to
talk about Pakistan's allegedly massive
oil reserves? Because his
business empire is massively invested in
Pakistan. You see Pakistan and India are
very different countries. In India, if
you want to invest in the oil and gas
gas sector, if you're Trump or if you're
any business person, if you're any
corporate entity from the west or
whatever, if you want to invest in
India's go oil and gas sector sector,
you have to play by the rules, right?
The government of India will set up the
rules and you do play by those rules.
And if you are investing in Pakistan,
well, Pakistan is ruled by the Pakistani
military and essentially the nation is
up for sale. As long as you will fill
the pockets of the Pakistani generals,
you can essentially plunder the nation's
resources entirely. So who benefits? The
generals and the military benefit and
the foreign entity benefits. The people
of Pakistan get nothing out of it.
That's the deal. So there's so much more
money to be made from exploiting
Pakistani oil reserves even if they may
be small compared to do the doing the
same in India because in India you can't
exploit them. You have to play by the
rules and India gets the major share of
the profits.
So Trump is out there. That's that's the
Pakistani military has obviously
naturally rolled out the red carpet for
for Trump. Pakistan is a land for sale.
The military is very happy
to sell out the country parcel by par
parcel and if Trump is the buyer, well,
they'll be very happy to sell it to. Why
it's not just all the oil and gas gas
sector in Pakistan which is quite small
but if Trump gets the whole the whole
pie well that's a tremendous amount of
money to be made there even if it's a
small oil and gas sector and Trump is
also investing in uh Trump's business
empire is also in investing in uh the
Pakistani um rare earth's mineral sector
whatever rare earths they have Trump
will get that and also their so-called
cryptocurrency sector which is a nassent
sector
So Trump he stands to make the total pie
is is about is valued around around $50
trillion if it can be extracted
exploited. So that's why Trump is so
bullish on Pakistan. So the oil reserves
are pretty small but Trump sees them as
as a big jackpot for himself right then
and that's why Trump is talking about
that and obviously Trump is not getting
what he wants from India. India is not
cowtowing. India is not genulecting in
front of Trump and that's why he's he's
upset and that's why he's taunting India
about this. All right, that's the deal.
So the the oil reserves do exist. Some
oil is there but it's nothing compared
to what we have in India or nothing
compared to what the the Gulf region has
and so on. But Trump is investing in
Pakistan and he's he's being given the
red carpet treatment, the royal
treatment and Trump loves that. Trump
needs people to be super differential to
him and treat him like he's the royalty
to end all royalty and that's why he's
so happy with Pakistan and is just so
upset about India. That's the deal
because India is standing up for itself.
India is showing a spine. India is
refusing to vasalize itself to Mr. Trump
and whoever runs his actual empire. Not
the business empire but the real
geopolitical empire. Uh so yeah that's a
real and that's why he is behaving the
way he is.
Okay, Ramshukla says, "What will be the
effect of 25% tariffs on India imposed
by the US and what could India do in
retaliation?" So, India ex So, I went
into this in detail. I don't remember
the exact numbers, but India exports.
So, this this this uh trade that happens
between the two countries in the value
is about 120 to1 130 billion roughly
total per year annually if I recall
correctly from yesterday's figures. uh
you can look into yesterday's episode of
geost strategy to get the exact figures
but it's around 130 or so trillion
billion dollars per year and there's a
significant trade imbalance in favor of
India
um so India may be exporting about 87
around 90 billion worth of goods to the
US per year okay roughly okay don't
quote me on that look at if there is
episode of ge strategy to get the exact
details uh so if Trump imposes which he
has done
u 25% tariffs on Indian goods. It means
that if something is worth $100, okay,
if I'm selling an item worth $100, once
it reaches the US, it's going to be
taxed 25% extra. It's going to cost $125
in the US. So it's it it puts me at a
significant disadvantage as an exporter
to the US because my products will not
be competitively priced and that gives
the American customer consumer uh an
incentive not to buy from me because my
products are higher are at a higher
price even if they may be perhaps better
than other products. So that's going to
affect India various Indian sectors.
Yeah. So what could India do in
retaliation and that's a great question.
I mean we need to look into that. What
can India do in retaliation? There's a
lot India can do in retal retaliation
and that that also I I went into
yesterday. So first of all we have
economic leverage. We control a 150
billion dollar plus services market uh
to the US particularly the IT sector but
and also the business process
outsourcing BO sector. many huge
American corporations, lots of Fortune
500 companies, most of them, Microsoft,
Google and whatnot, they all depend on
Indian IT talent, Indian service
centers, right? So, if we disrupt that,
it could immediately impact American
corporation corporate operations. Um,
lots of Indian lots of American
companies are dependent on this. Then,
um, America's the US is super dependent
on India for pharmaceuticals. India
supplies approximately 40% of the
genetic drugs to the US market where
they may be rebranded or whatever right
so if we put a restriction on that that
will create an immediate healthcare
crisis in the US and that will create a
tremendous political backlash uh on
Trump right um then India could
obviously impose reciprocal tariffs on
American goods they could impose 25%
tariffs on goods right we could uh
target various sectors uh and that would
be a problem for the US now The
Americans they depend on Indian H1B visa
talent. They always keep craving about
H1B visas that Indian H1B visa holders
are taking away our jobs and all but the
moment we stop the H-1B visas and we say
that Indians can no longer apply for H1B
visas which which the government of
India can do then it will the US
tech sector its operations within weeks
or months. If we even make a take a more
drastic step and say that all H1B visa
holders need to come back to India
immediately we can do that. That will
destroy the US tech sector. and how will
they replace all that talent? It'll
create a crisis in the US. Then India
could withdraw from the crow quad and so
many other things. If you want to see
the details, look into yesterday's
episode of geo strategy in which I have
gone into the the specific details of
what India can do. There's so much India
can do. There's a lot of leverage that
we have. So it's not like we are sitting
ducks. This is not the India of 2020.
It's not the India of 1991. It's a whole
different India today. Obviously that
will cause a tremendous amount of pain
to us also because they also have way
more leverage than us. But do we really
want to play this game? You want to
unleash a proper trade war, tariff war,
all kind of yeah hostilities. Why what's
the point? The better option is to sit
down, negotiate and find a negotiated
mutually acceptable, mutually beneficial
uh solution. A good deal, a good deal, a
good settlement is one in which there is
pain on both sides. Okay? You can't have
a situation where only one side only
when you have two negotiating parties,
only one party must bear the pain and
the other guy gets everything. That's
not going to happen. And when both sides
of leverage, it doesn't happen. There
has to be some pain on both sides.
Okay? So, let's see how it goes. The
Americans are are employ are adopting a
maximalist stance. They're making
maximalist demands. That's Trump's
preferred way of negotiating, but it's
not working out with India and that's
why he's so upset. You see, that is the
deal.
Right. Pray says, "How damaging was
Trump's recent outburst against India,
dismissing the world's fastest growing
major economy with such contempt? Has he
crossed a line that could irreparably
strain the personal Modi Trump? Is this
just raw frustration or a desperate
display of power from a presidency
facing economic decline? And above all,
is such rhetoric even befitting of a
leader seeking global credibility?
Well, it certainly is damaging. Will it
irreparably strain the Modi Trump
rapport, the personal rapport?
Maybe not. See, Mr. Modi is a very
pragmatic, very practical person.
He doesn't allow personal slights,
personal insults to come between him and
his pursuit of the national interest.
And we have seen that in the past the
Democrats, the Americans, the US
administration had imposed a ban on Mr.
Modi visiting the US, right?
This was done when he was the chief
minister of Gujarat, right? But when Mr.
Modi became the prime minister, uh that
ban obviously was no longer valid,
right? He is now a global leader. So he
did not allow that incident to cause any
lingering bitterness and he went ahead
and embraced Mr. Obama and did whatever
it took to
strengthen the relationship between
India and the US because it's in the
interest of India. So Mr. Modi you know
he doesn't allow these things to come in
the way of the national interest. So in
the future if there's an opportunity
which there could be if there's an
opportunity in the future uh to take
steps and actions which will take India
US relations in the in the in a forward
positive direction and it'll be better
for India that way then Mr. Modi will
disregard what's happened thus far.
Disregard everything Mr. Trump has said
and he will go again and embrace Mr.
Trump as if they they've always been
best friends. That's what Mr. Modi does.
Yeah. So I I don't think it's it's going
to irreparably strain the rapport.
Obviously, there's a strain right now.
I'm not sure if the two leaders have
spoken for a while. Maybe not since the
uh operation Synindur uh the end the
secession of hostilities which happened
on May 10 and Trump immediately claimed
that he was responsible for the alleged
ceasefire. Well, I don't think the two
leaders may have spoken since then. I
may be wrong, of course. Uh
but I don't think it's going to cause a
per a permanent strain as long as Mr.
Mr. Trump matters. Mr. Modi will give
him due respect, due difference, due
importance more than difference probably
not difference but importance. And if
Mr. Trump requires some difference and
if it will
take us forward in the right direction
and and and uh help us achieve something
some better outcomes for the national
interest, he will even do that. So
that's deal. Uh now how damaging has
this outburst been? It's been pretty
damaging actually. It's been pretty
damaging. The whatever trust existed
whatever see we have never been very
trusting of the US with very good
reason. Look at their actions in the
past. Look at the entire pattern. And
now people will say that I am being a
going harking back to the cold war. You
know what a nation if you want to
understand its true nature its true
character its true uh modus operandi you
have to look at its entire history
you know to see how it behaves
and if you look at the US behavior since
1945 you go back you will see it's
always been anti-India it's essentially
taken on the mantle of the British
Empire it's the the continuation of the
British Empire and they they still are
very strongly anti-India they see India
as a problem right But we have made
significant strides in the past 10 years
or so in uh you know strengthening the
US India relationship and we've even
purchased American weapons systems and
whatnot right we know that now whatever
trust existed
has kind of been damaged especially when
it comes to comes to defense cooperation
because when Trump and the US
establishment once again go back and
take Pakistan's side like they did in
May. Well, that makes all trust
evaporate. We will still continue
economic cooperation wherever possible.
Defense cooperation is finished.
It's finished.
It's that's how damaging Trump's
behavior has been. And of course, we
know what the Americans have been doing
the past few years. They they've created
a new vasal state in East Pakistan.
That's an anti-India move. They created
project K, Cookand for Christ. that is
still ongoing.
Manipur is bleeding. The the people of
Manipur, you have no idea how much
they're suffering right now.
Half of I don't know how many foreigners
are squatting on Manipur territory.
That's all geopolitical actions taken by
a far away force. So all of this is
being done
to cut India down to size. So there is
no not not going to be any trust now
when it comes to from India's
perspective from from our perspective
towards the US we don't trust them
they're out to dismantle us
the ideal outcome for the US long-term
is the bulcanization of India trust me
that's the outcome every action they
take
on the ground is in that direction
whether it is the industrial scales
Christianization of the subcontinent
which they are funding with possibly
trillions of dollars every year and
whatever else they're doing they're out
see how do you bulcanize a country like
India by bringing in a subversive
foreign religion and
re-engineering the demographics of the
country and uh look it's not me who
claims this it's the Japanese and the
Chinese who have claimed this that see
the Japanese wrote about this in the I
don't know which 17th 18th 19th century
whenever they wrote about this that
whenever Japanese people were converted
to Christianity they somehow who
spontaneously developed extr territorial
ter territorial loyalties. The Japanese
wrote about this. The Chinese wrote
about this. So it's a pattern.
This is a weapon and they're using that
against India. So I think the trust is
gone.
There will be economic cooperation
wherever required. It's going to be
issue based cooperation. It's going to
be tactical level cooperation. There's
no strategic convergence between India
and the US. That's over.
Yeah. So yeah that's what I can say.
Um Rakkesh Masri says what's going on in
the India US relationship? Is isn't this
a suicidal movement on the perspective
of future strategy? US tariffs can
destroy the Indian economy is India say
is it a question or is it a statement?
What's going on in the India US
relationship? I'll tell you what's going
on. See at the topmost level in the
world there is competition between the
US and China. The US believes it can
manage China.
China you the US knows all they have to
wait do is wait 20 30 years.
China will reach a certain peak and then
it will decline. The the main reason for
the decline is going to be China's in um
China's upcoming demographic disaster.
China's birth rates have collapsed
drastically dramatically. China is
aging. China's population is going to
collapse eventually. It's going to
happen in slow motion, but it's going to
cause an irreversible decline in China.
China's going to going to go down the
same way as Japan. Now, they're going to
use technology and robotics and AI to to
bolster up national power, but the US
knows they can manage China. And the US
is in the lead when it comes to AI and
other things. And they're trying to
they're trying their best to keep China
down in terms of semic semiconductor
technology and all that. And they have
way more nuclear weapons and so on. So,
the US thinks they believe that they can
manage China. They also believe that
they can manage Russia,
right? Russia has certain handicaps and
problems that the Americans believe that
they can exploit to manage Russia. They
can bog Russia down in Ukraine. They can
open new fronts if needed and whatever.
Now, the third problem, there are other
problems as well, but those are being
dealt with by causing mass immigration
into Europe and destabilizing the
European demographics and economy and
whatnot. Africa doesn't really matter
because they've already ruined it in the
past. What other nations exist? There's
only one problem which is India right
the EU can be managed NATO nations can
be managed India needs to now what about
India India is a nation that if left
alone and allowed to grow it will
naturally sp even with all the problems
that you have in India it will still
eventually regain its natural position
India's natural position for the past
200 plus years has been the world's
largest economy today's Indians will not
be able to believe it because you've
been you you were born in a at a time
when India was at its
peak at the at the not the peak the
opposite the nadier of India's misery
India was forcibly de-industrialized and
destroyed India's economy was destroyed
but India will again come back and
that's a problem for the US
and that's why they don't want that to
happen and so that's what that that that
explains everything they are doing visav
India now from their perspective well
maybe they are right if I were the
biggest power in the some new upstart
were showing signs of resuming their
natural behavior. I would want to
balconize and destroy them. Right?
Thusidity trap. Don't even allow the the
the the possibility of a future
situation where you have a suicidality
trap kind of scenario. Don't even allow
that to happen. Nip the problem in the
bud. So from their perspective, they are
doing what they should do. So I nothing
personally, right? But that's what the
deal is. And that that's what explains
what's happening. Now suicidal movement
on who's whose part? our part. No, we
not we we are standing up for for
ourselves. We have two options. Stand up
for ourselves and take some pain, maybe
a lot of pain, or just become another
vasal once again and go down the road
which led us to the East India Company
and another 250 years of slavery.
So maybe those 250 years of slavery will
be nice for the general public. You may
have access to nice gadgets and
reasonable comfort and all but your
civilization will be destroyed.
you will all end up your children will
end up worshiping a different god and
they will no longer have any connection
to to our ancestors our civilization.
So I don't think that's a viable option
for us. Um so that is what is happening
right this is India is going to have 20
years at least of pain minimum it's just
beginning but listen if you want
greatness in the future you've got to go
through pain otherwise you choose
embrace mediocrity and most Indians are
happy to do that unfortunately right now
but uh what's happening what what the
government of India is doing is the
right thing we're standing up for
ourselves we are refusing
to or on vizage scenario B that I spoke
about Yesterday I've been speaking about
four scenarios for the past month. I
forecast four scenarios in the India US
relationship. The trajectory I forecast
four scenarios on the 1st of July.
Scenario B was India becoming a
reluctant vasal of the US. That's not
happening. That scenario is not
materializing. We are witnessing maybe a
combination of scenario C and D. If you
want to see the scenarios, please watch
yesterday's episode of Geost Strategy in
which I've laid it out. All right.
Shri Ramachandraayan Namaha says if
Trump receives the Nobel Peace Prize
award will he become passive after that?
Well, Mr. Trump greatly desires that.
Mr. Trump greatly desires the Nobel
Peace Prize, right? Uh he does greatly
desire it, but it won't uh stop him. It
won't make him passive. Look, Mr. Trump
has been a driven person all his life.
He's been an entrepreneur. He's been a
businessman his entire life. He's been a
driven man,
right? He's been very driven and
whatever he's achieved, he was he it has
not stopped him from immediately wanting
more. I achieved this now I want more.
It's not going to be enough. So it he
will not become passive after that. I
think he will see that as a vindication
that he was right all the all along and
now he will redouble his his efforts to
do whatever he's doing if he receives
the Nobel Peace Prize. He's not the kind
of person who will stop. And that's a an
admirable quality, by the way. It's an
admirable quality.
There are lots of people who are super
talented and all, but they don't have
the persistence, the drive to to run
through brick walls to get what they
want. Mr. Trump does have it. So if he
receives the Nobel Peace Prize, he will
take that as the vindication
as as the fact that as as the
vindication that he was right all along
and now that he's got this and he has
been vindicated, he should redouble his
efforts in whatever direction he's
going. So it's not going to make him
passive. It's going to make him twice as
active. That's how I see it.
Ulas says will the coming days be hard
for India as Pakistan is having a
three-way a minage atwa with China and
the US as both nations have some seem to
have some kind of agreement when it
comes to India.
So the first question basic question
overall question is will the coming days
be hard for India? I just said in one of
the previous answers it's going to be a
tough 20 years for India and India is
going to be there's always going to be
the temptation every single day let's
just give up and become a US fasal
everything will settle down everything
will be solved right always there's
always going to be that temptation
there's always the easy way out let's
say you are climbing Mount Everest you
just started
what do you do should you look up the
moment you look up you're going to want
to give up so what you do when you're
climbing Mount Everest is you never look
up. You just look at the next six feet.
You put one hand in front of the other,
one foot in front of the other, and you
keep going. You keep going. You count to
10, 10 steps, then you reset to zero.
Then you count to 10 and you take
checkpoints and you take and then you
take it one day at a time. Maybe one
hour at a time,
right? That's how we do it. And it gets
tougher and tougher and tougher as you
go on further and further and further
ahead. And every single second, every
single time your heart beats, there is
the option that you know I don't have to
go through this pain. I can always go
back down and all the pain, all the
misery will be immediately over.
So then it all depends on what you what
the stuff that you're made of. How much
fortitude do you have? Do you really
desire what you set out to do or was
this just something that you dreamt of
one day and it did not really matter for
you? So the coming days will be hard for
India. It's going to be a hard 20 years.
But if it does if India does endure and
push through the pain of the next 20
years, then we're going to be a whole
different beast by that time.
So the the temptation of option B a tilt
to the west and U and vasage of the US
that's always going to be there option B
the temptation of option B right but we
cannot allow that to happen now about
now the other question about the
three-way in Pakistan US and and and
China yeah there is indeed some kind of
understanding see Pakistan is a
disposable asset it's a throwaway asset
Pakistan is a nation with no future. I'm
sorry to say that. Nothing against the
people of Pakistan but Pakistan is a
temporary artificial nation which was
created with a singular purpose. That
purpose was to serve western
geopolitical interests in the India
Indian subcontinent plus region which
includes the Gulf region as well West
Asia that whole region you need a
mercenary
of your own who will serve you. That's
why Pakistan was created and right now
it's it's got great um utility for
whoever wants to use it as a
counterbalance to India as a nation that
can be used to on demand
issue pain towards India and create
problems for India. Right? And Pakistan
is not run for its people. The
government of Pakistan is non-existent.
the the entity that actually owns
Pakistan is the Pakistani military and
they are a mercenary organization and
they will serve whichever master gives
them what they wants which is more and
more cash to send to those bank accounts
wherever they are in the world. Their
families are will typically be living in
the west.
So now both the US and China agree on
one thing and one thing only that India
needs to be contained.
Okay. So the US is happy to use India if
possible as a leverage against China as
a counterbalance to China but not in a
way that will make India stronger.
Use India in various ways which will
damage India also and also damage China.
And the greatest ideal situation is
India and China go to war and bash each
other's brains out and destroy each
other which India and China are capable
of doing. That's the ideal situation for
the US and then they can just once India
and China are done with each other and
destroyed then the US can focus on the
remaining adversary which is Russia.
Yep. So and of course uh and and China
believes that you know whatever happens
they can deal with the US and they don't
need India on their side. So that's the
thing. So both the US and China are
using Pakistan against India. The US is
okay with Pakistan being used by China
as long as it is something detrimental
to India.
The US is fine with that.
Right? Uh so they have Trump has imposed
25% tariffs on India only 19% tariffs on
on Pakistan despite Pakistan being
halfway in bed with China. So there is
an understanding there's only one thing
that US and China agree on that India
needs to be contained. They disagree on
everything else.
So it's going to be a problem for India
and it's going to be a tough 20 years
ahead and we will need good leaders not
good leadership we'll need tremendously
great leadership.
If we mess up with our leadership if we
in the future one of these days have a
leader who is less capable
than Mr. Modi, we're done.
We're done. That's it.
Rene Paul says, "How do you assess
India's sudden halt in Russian oil
purchases by state refiners? Is this a
strategic recalibration or the result of
mounting US pressure behind the scenes?
And what does this shift signal for
India's energy security and India's
balancing act in great power
geopolitics?
oil. So this is something that I did
discuss briefly yesterday in yesterday's
episode of geostrategy
which may be a pivotal episode in the
history of geo geostrategy episodes.
So yesterday the news came out indeed
that India has paused its uh Indian
state refiners have paused purchases of
Russian oil. That's what one heard right
but today it has emerged that there is
no such thing.
So yesterday I did say that you know
we've the news has emerged that there is
a pause but it seems to be driven by
market demand and pressures rather than
a policy move and what I said yesterday
what I speculated yesterday has kind of
been vindicated by the news that came
out today. Let's quickly take a look at
at at if possible the news. Uh India
Russian oil India Russian oil purchases
purchase. What's it say? India
continuing to buy oil from Russia.
Report rebutts Donald Trump's good steps
forever. India will continue to buy oil
from Russia. That's what Reuters says.
Uh Trump cites some reports on India
halting Russian oil imports. India to
still buy oil from Russia despite Trump
threats say Indian officials and
yesterday there was this news that this
news that Indian state refiners halted
Russian oil purchases. Well, not going
to happen. Sorry. India is continuing to
buy Russian oil. India will continue
that Indian refineries will continue to
buy oil from Russia before and so on.
So there we have it. So this is clearly
uh not the case. Uh India is going to
continue to purchase Russian oil.
India's national interest comes before
the national interest of other countries
right and uh we have excellent relations
with Russia we are getting good prices
from Russia we have a relationship of
trust with Russia unlike with other some
other countries right uh so yeah it's
it's not some sudden halt we're going to
continue our oil purchases from Russia
why should we not in the past the
Americans did arm twist us in into
stopping our oil purchases from another
friend of ours, Persia, Iran. We used to
buy a lot of oil from from Iran and then
the Americans armed in India into
stopping our oil purchases from Iran and
that well that was bad for India. We
could have actually gone ahead and
developed the Forza B or whatever it was
oil field in the Persian Gulf. That also
we could not do because we stopped
purchas oil purchases from Iran and then
Iran said that if you're not purchasing
oil from us then why should you get the
right to develop our oil field? So there
was a huge missed opportunity for us and
it was all because of US arm twisting.
It impacted our national interest. It's
not going to be allowed to happen
anymore. Right? So uh that is the
situation. So the shift actually is that
we are going to continue our oil
purchases from Russia and that's a
message to Trump
that our national interest comes first
and foremost. Your whims and fancies are
are your problem, right? So yeah, I
think it's a good step. It's a tough
step. It's going to cause pain to us,
but it's the right step.
India is the one nation apart from
Russia and China that's standing up the
to the US. Would you believe it? Would
you believe it? Here we are.
Okay. Rahul Dun says, Trump says, and
I'm paraphrasing, Pakistan is sitting on
tons of crude oil which we could extract
in Pakistan would trade it from India
with India. Does the news of andammans
having trillions of gallons of crude oil
that could make India 20 trillion dollar
economy a thing to balance Trump's
nonsense? Yes. So Trump has made all
these all these statements about
Pakistan allegedly having tremendous oil
reserves and one day maybe Pakistan will
trade with India because Trump is so
powerful he'll make it happen. Yeah.
That's what he says. That's what he
claims. Now the so then what does the
and thing the this the news about and
potential and demand oil reserves have?
How does that factor into this? That's
the question.
So, we haven't had an official
announcement yet of a major oil
discovery in the Andaman region, right?
But you know what? India is a gigantic
place. Let's let's open the maps. It's
been 37 minutes. I haven't opened the
map yet. So, here we go. Let's look at
the map. India is a gigantic region.
Look at this. How large India is. I
mean, Indians are used to this map and
they think it's a small place. India is
gigantic.
It is inconceivable
that India won't have huge oil reserves
in multiple locations,
right? It's inconceivable. Now, India is
currently drilling in the Andaman Sea
region and uh the minister Mr. Hadep
Singh Puri I I believe recently said
that it's just a matter of time before
we strike strike oil and and discover a
Guyana sized oil you know oil reserve in
the Andermans. Well I think you know
what you should say these things only
when you actually discover something
don't count your chickens before the
hatch. So I'm not sure what the why the
minister said what he said why we
actually discovered something. My point
is we need to redouble our efforts into
in our drilling in in drilling and and
prospecting for oil and we need to
discover whatever oil reserves we have.
We have hardly done anything in
prospecting for oil. The one place
west of Maharashtra in the in the Indian
Ocean region it's called Bombay High or
something. It's one place where we we've
discovered oil and we have some some
places in Assam. We have never bothered
to look into how much reserves we have.
If we do it properly, we'll find
tremendous oil. I think it's high time
we do that.
India's achilles heel right now
geopolitically
is us
uh not being self-sufficient in terms of
energy. That's a huge Achilles heel. It
means that we are dependent on other
countries for our basic energy
requirements. I think we import more
than 60 70 or maybe 80% of our oil and
gas from other countries.
So if those countries are pressurized
into not selling oil to India, we are in
deep deep deep trouble.
We need to
we need to consider this a matter of the
highest priority, highest urgency,
national security, the discovery of new
oil reser reserves. uh so it's I think
it's very possible if we just look
everywhere especially in regions where
you know you would have a higher
likelihood like the Andamani region
right uh we need to make the discovery
as soon as possible if if that happens
it'll take us I would say at least 5
years to operationalize oil extraction
once that happens well we will need way
more naval resources
to safeguard our oil reserves which
means that we will need more destroyers
bought submarines what not which is a
good news which is great news so I think
it needs to happen as soon as possible
it's it's a matter of the highest
priority that we discover huge oil reser
reserves I mean it's inconceivable that
we don't have it such a huge
subcontinent no oil I mean are you
kidding me so we've been super lazy our
leaders in the past have been super lazy
they've never bothered to do anything
they just depend on imports maybe it
maybe there so who knows what reasons
behind that um yeah so if if slash when
we make these oil discoveries well that
will be a total gamecher it'll
immediately transform India's GDP and
all that so it needs to happen until and
unless it happens there's no point
talking about it
says do you do you agree it's a bipolar
world we living in and China and the US
are leading it and we are not on either
side non-alignment policy is working
today or do we need to change something
in our foreign policy should we align
with some power Russia India, China can
be a solid trio but we can't trust
China. Aligning with the US will affect
our relations with with Russia and
weakening our local dairy and farmer
industries situation is really complex.
Uh are we living in a bipolar world?
Well, there are two major blocks
geopolitical blocks. There is the US-led
block which is the US and its minions or
the US and its vasals, right? That's the
US plus NATO plus EU and plus the Japan
and South Korea and various other
nations under US occupation or under US
subjugation hegemony right that's one
group of nations that's the it's a huge
group of nations the other group is
China and Russia and North Korea and
whoever else may so that's that's
essentially in India Iran that's four
nations
now India has good relations excellent
relations with with Russia
We have good relations with Iran. So
essentially we have two major blocks.
The US and its vasals and you have
China, Russia, Iran, North Korea. That's
the second block. And then you have a
whole bunch of nations
who are called the global south and the
most powerful and the largest one is
India out of all these. Now India is not
aligned with anybody. Uh so it's not
quite a bipolar world. It's kind of a
world that's drifting towards
bipolarity. both China and the US would
want a bipolar world right now it's a
multipolar world kind of kind of
multipolar
right um so is now is India
using a non-align alignment policy we're
not we are multi-aligned this is not
non-alignment
uh this is multi-alignment we are
aligned with multiple nations wherever
wherever our national interests lie and
they converge with those of other
nations we are aligned with them in
those things it's multi-alignment it's
working fine for us and that's how the
world actually should
Right? Uh do we need to change something
in our foreign policy? Should we align
with some power? Well, if you align with
a more powerful nation, you have to you
have to bend
to their demands. There there's a cost
of alignment. There are conditions for
alignment.
It's not just okay we say that okay now
we are aligned with you. It's not like
that. It doesn't work like that. There
are conditions that need to be
fulfilled. There are steps you to take.
For example, let me give you an example.
If a nation in Europe wants to become a
member of NATO, they going to what are
the conditions and requirements for
becoming a NATO member? Let me show you
in case you are not aware. There's so
much they need to change about their own
internal working. For example, uh
requirements or how about a EU member
requirements
for becoming EU member
member? What am I saying ma'am? Okay. To
become a member of the EU, a country
must first and foremost be European.
Okay. Beyond this, they must also meet
the Copenhagen criteria which include
having stable institutions guaranteeing
democracy, the rule of law, human
rights, respect for minorities,
a functioning market economy, and the
ability to scope with competitive cope
with competitive pressures within the
EU. The complete the applicant country
must align its laws with the aquis,
the body of EU law and be willing to
commit to the objectives of whatever
political, economic and monetary union.
and and there's a whole set of accession
process formal application negotiations
agreement and ratification conditions
for membership enlargement Copenhagen
criteria so once you apply for
membership you have to make certain
changes in your country okay um
there's a whole set of things you to do
which essentially change the way your
country is is run and all that you have
to no longer be who you are it would be
you to become something else so that
for becoming a member of the EU. Then
there are a set of criteria for becoming
a member of NATO. You're welcome to, but
you have to change things. Essentially,
you to place your military under a
foreigner's command. A foreigner will
command your military essentially. So,
if you want to align yourself with the
US, for example, they're going to
intrude all over all they'll penetrate
the whole country and all the
institutions to some extent. They've
already done that by the way. So, it'll
be a disaster for India. We'll no longer
be a sovereign entity. Alignment means
losing sovereignty.
Okay. So we are not aligned with any
power. We should not align with any
power. Um Russia India China can be a
solid trio but China has always been the
spoiler. China believes that it is it is
way ahead of India and India is beneath
aligning with India or having good
relations with India is beneath China's
dignity and they they think they can
manage India through tremendous all
kinds of pressure various pressure
tactics that that used in the past so
that's what China can China believes now
right now they are doing some kind of
there could be the potential of some
kind of haphosima between India and
China some kind of the taunt that's been
going on for some for some time we're
going to have to be very careful about
China Yeah, because China's track record
tells us that they cannot be trusted.
I'm sorry. Nothing personal against
China. The Chinese people are wonderful.
We've had tremendous relations between
India and China for the past 2,000
years. But since the 1950s, things have
changed. And the Chinese Communist
Party, its policies uh make it an
untrustworthy entity from our
perspective.
So, RIC would be a great idea, but only
if China behaves. They don't want to
behave.
um they they don't want allies, they
don't want partners, they want vasals.
They want Russia to become a vasal.
Okay? And they are working assiduously
in that direction, towards that
direction. Uh aligning with the US means
India becomes a vasal and a
non-soververeign entity. Forget about
the relations with with Russia. We will
cease to exist as a as as a civilization
to whatever extent we still to whatever
extent we still do exist as a
civilization. And it will weaken all our
dairy, all our industries. It's going to
be the East India company days all over
again. We're going to be a market. We're
going to be an importing market. We'll
import everything from outsiders and we
will export services.
It's going to be game over for India.
So, not a good idea. We're going to have
to swallow 20 years of pain.
Right. Okay. Amisha says, "If Trump had
really truly offered a trade deal to
India to push a ceasefire with Pakistan,
he wouldn't have done this today. Done
this. Done what?" Okay. Um, yeah. The
25% tariffs, I suppose. Yeah. Uh, Trump
has outed himself. He's really angry,
clearly angry about India. He's a liar.
Should we restart Operation Zindur in
full form? Um, can India retired with
its own tariffs on US goods? Push to
restart trade talks? What are our
options? So like I said in a one of the
previous answers, we do have a lot of
leverage, economic leverage, strategic
leverage, e geopolitical leverage. Um we
can have alternative partnerships, we
can have asymmetric different responses.
If you want the details of all the kinds
of leverage that we have, some of the
leverage that we have look look at watch
that section of yesterday's episode of
Geost Strategy. We have leverage, but
they have more leverage. Obviously, they
are much more powerful nation, way more
powerful nation. So if we go down that
road, it's going to be like, you know,
it's going to be a trade war and and
it'll escalate and it's not going to be
at the end of the day, we're going to
come out second best. So we should
obviously go for some kind of trade
deal. We should and that's what we are
doing. Our government has reacted very
maturely. We have not thrown any
tantrums. We have not used any uh
Trump-like language. For example, we
have said that you know what, we want
very much to have a trade deal and we
would like to go ahead with the trade
talks and see what what's the best thing
we can achieve. Um, and we have not
imposed retal retaliatory tariffs thus
far. So this obviously is a leverage
that Trump is trying to use on us. This
is not a final position that he has
taken 25% tariffs. He depending on how
we negotiate, he may be willing to bring
it down depending on what we offer him.
Obviously, he wants everything, right?
So, it's like this. Here's the options
Trump is giving us right now. You guys
are in bed with Russia. You're buying
Russian oil. So, 25% tariffs on you and
I may increase it to 500%. But let's
talk. And if you offer me your
sovereignty and your vasalhood, I'll
bring 25% down to 20%.
That's it. Or 19% like Pakistan. I'll
treat you just like Pakistan. So become
my vasal and I will treat you like
Pakistan. Otherwise tariffs, big
tariffs, tremendous tariffs, big
beautiful tariffs. So that's the choice
we have India. Either we swallow the
pain of 25% or more tariffs or
we capitulate and then we get the
privilege of being treated by Trump just
the way he treats Pakistan.
What's the right option? India what's
the right option please let me know
okay okay big question long questions
Akash says sar western powers like the
US use economic sanctions as weapons yes
sir we know that much like how the east
India company controlled weaker nations
that's correct
same modus operandi if India builds
naval dominance over the Indian ocean
using cheap missile boats armed with
missiles I I've heard that somewhere and
drones and gains control over choke
points like the straight of Mala,
Hormuz, Bab al-Mandde and the Muzad big
channel. Can this give real can this
give India a real advantage? If India
ever blocks these sea lanes, global
trade, especially the oil and goods
would be disrupted and the world economy
as well, including the US would be badly
hit. Can such control help India resist
sanctions and make our economy more
secure? Okay, interesting question.
Let's look at the map and let's look at
these choke points that you are
referring to. What are these choke choke
choke points? Let's see
here we are here is map. Yes. So one of
the choke points is the straight of
hormos the straight of
over here and much of the energy that
that the world needs flows through this
choke point. Then you have the straight
of Bab al-mandib which is here between
jihuti and ye then you have the
mozzambique channel over here. Right.
That's a that's kind of a joke point.
Sure. Uh then we have uh the straight of
Malaa and you also have another say
straight over here. Okay, this one uh
what's it called? I don't remember but
this is another uh choke point that is
an alternative to the to the straight of
Mala. So these are some of the most
important most vital choke points that
we can theoretically
uh cut off if we have a sufficiently
capable navy and a sufficiently
strong willed political leadership.
Right.
So we could do that. Now the question is
this. Question is this. Let's think of
second order effects.
Don't
reduce yourself and don't be content
with surface level analysis my friends.
At least do think like a see don't you
don't need to think like a grandmaster.
Think like a chess player. A a decent
chess player will think three four moves
ahead.
A grandmaster I believe thinks 15 moves
ahead possibly. But a decent chess
player who has some self-respect will at
least think think three four moves
ahead. So now let's say let's let's do
some
forward thinking
proper analysis decently proper
analysis. Let's say India develops a
more powerful navy and we are able to
blockade the straight of Malaka the
straight of a mazda the straight of Bab
al-Manddev the straight of tears the
straight of the bambic channel and and
the straight of Malaka. Let's say we are
capable of doing that. Okay. So we now
have a theoretically hypothetically a
situation where India has a more
powerful navy, a blue water navy and in
we can choke off we can blockade
multiple choke points at the same time.
Okay. Then what happens?
Does this does this give us tremendous
leverage?
No.
It possibly can. But if we blockade
these choke points, what could be the
response of other powers? Pakistan is
not another power. It can't do a thing.
Fine, good. Iran, well, Iran may be
upset because they are selling oil
wherever and we are locatedating that.
But they probably can't do much because
they don't have a very powerful navy,
air force, whatever. Obviously, we don't
want to upset Iran. Why would we? They
we're on good terms with them. But we
are looking at the hypothetical
scenario. So, let's say Pakistan can't
do anything. Iran can't do anything. uh
the Gulf nations can't do much. Okay. If
we blockade Mala,
what will China do?
China may divert its navy towards
Malaca. Then there'll be a naval
showdown between India and China. China
has the world's largest navy
numerically.
Yeah. What happens then?
They have they typically have more
missiles per war per per uh destroyer
than India does.
So that gives them a straightforward
numerical advantage. Yeah. China and
India if even if if if even if India
doubles its naval power. I think China
still comes up comes out on top.
Yeah. Do we want that situation? And
let's say we blockade other some
whatever other strait and the US gets
upset. Obviously they'll get upset
because they are no longer controlling
the region, right? What if there's a
naval showdown between India and the US?
Do we want a situation like that ever to
happen? And if there's a showdown,
there's a fight, who wins? The US wins.
So India gets gets real leverage only if
we
only if we able to build a global top
three navy.
One of the top three navies in the world
in terms of firepower,
not in terms of number of ships. How do
you measure the strength of a navy? Do
you measure the strength of a navy by
the number of ships that you have,
number of assets you can deploy? No,
that's not the only factor. It's a good
factor. But the real
measure of a navy's firepower and
strength is how many missiles can you
deploy at sea on any given day missiles.
So that's these are the factors we need
to look into. India can give can gain
real leverage only if we build a top
three or top two navy. Only if we can
surpass either the the US or China. Not
even top three but top two.
Only then will we get leverage that will
be tremendous leverage. That will be
tremendous leverage. India already has
the money and the resources to build a
top two navy. India has it. Yeah. So you
you don't merely need a navy that can
blockade the choke points. You need a
navy that can blockade and sustain the
blockade and defeat anybody who
challenges you. That's what you need.
It's not enough to build some kind of
naval dominance and say, "Oh, I can
blockade this, blockade that." That is
not enough. So, if you can do that, then
you can negotiate anything on the table.
Even with the US, you can arm twist
them. If you have this because political
power and negotiating power it flows out
of the barrel of a gun as Maatung once
said right that's what needs to happen
so we need we need some ambition we need
leaders with ambition we have the money
but I don't know where the money is
going what schemes is it going into
whatever all rightanka
biswas says can a genuine India China
only occur if India demonstrates
credible strength and strategic muscle
both militarily and diplomatically to
command mutual respect and engagement.
See,
you can't have, you're absolutely right,
in in in geopolitics, in international
relations, in all relations, what
matters is respect.
You won't treat somebody as an equal or
somebody as as uh worthy of being taken
seriously until you respect them. And
what what is it that makes somebody
respect you?
Fear. In the law of the jungle, if you
fear someone, you respect them, right?
When I was a kid, I had a cat. I had
many cats as a kid. So, I had this cat.
And this cat goes out, okay? Goes out.
And then I see the cat, my cat, and he's
just standing there with his hair raised
up. And he's being extremely
differential to somebody. I go and see
who it is. It's a small green snake.
small green snake, little snake. And my
cat was very nasty with snakes, okay? He
would do bad things to snakes. But this
snake was just standing there. And my
cat was saying, "Please sir, please,
please go ahead. Please, I will wait as
long as you need to wait and please go
ahead. Please go first." My cat was
being super differential. Why was he
being super differential? Because that
was a venomous snake.
That snake was capable of killing. Now,
cats have faster reaction times than
snakes. Even cats can even kill venomous
snakes. Why take the risk? So if the guy
has a weapon that can kill you, you're
going to respect the guy. You're going
to respect him. So that's the law of the
jungle. That's the law of nature. And
that is also the law of geopolitics,
right? So the Chinese don't respect
India right now. And would you blame
them for not respecting India? What has
India do done to earn their respect? The
only way to earn someone's respect is by
standing up for yourself and
demonstrating that you can hit back as
well as they can if not if not worse
than they can. Right? So you got to
demonstrate some spine. Right now India
is actually doing that. India is
standing up to the US. We are standing
up to them economically and g and
diplomatically not militarily. But yeah,
that that will
begrudgingly
engender some respect in Beijing. And we
and what we did in operation sindu, even
if it was just a three-day war, well,
that also will change some of the
perceptions that other nations have
towards India. Until and unless China
respects India, which means fears India,
uh there can no not be any genuine India
China. No, they don't. India has to
demonstrate credible strength, credible
fortitude. India needs to stand up for
itself. India needs to be able capable,
willing, capable and able to take pain
and still stand straight and push back.
You do these things, everyone will take
you seriously and you will not no longer
be the pushover in the room. So India is
going in that direction but India has a
long way to go. So yeah, that's the only
way you get Raproma with China. Only if
they genuinely respect you, which means
they fear you. You've got to make them
fear you. Even if you have no intention
of harming somebody, you've got to be
dangerous.
You see what's the difference?
What's the difference between a harmless
person and a dangerous person? A person,
no. See, a weak person, a weak person
who says that I'm good because I don't
hurt anybody. He's not a good person.
He's just weak.
He's just a weak. That's just a weak
person. That's not a good person. You
have no choice but to not harm anyone
otherwise you're going to be bashed up
because you are so weak. But a strong
person who is skilled in all forms of
violence who still and who despite being
so strong and despite being skilled in
violence if that person still chooses
not to hurt or harm anybody that's a
good person. So that's what India has to
be. Our our civilization our our
cultural values are that we have to we
should be nonviolent and not create any
mayhem in the world. Sure, it doesn't
mean that we should be weak. It means
that we should be strong enough to
resist anybody but still choose not to
not to be a hegemonic power. That's what
India needs to do. That's what needs to
happen. And only then can we gain the
respect of everybody else, our dance
partners, whoever they are, one is
China. So I think we are taking steps in
that direction now by standing up to the
US. That will I I promise you that will
raise some eyebrows in Beijing and that
will bring India a little amount of
grudging respect from from the Chinese.
Okay. Pray Paul says, "Was Microsoft's
move to block NRA Energy's access a mere
technical action or a calculated test of
control by the company or its
geopolitical masters? What does this
reveal about digital sovereignty and the
risks to India's critical
infrastructure?" So Naara Energy is an
Indian oil refining company. It has I
think India's second largest refinery or
something like that. Yeah. Uh and
and this company has been sanctioned by
the EU. The EU the European Union
European Union has imposed sanctions on
Nara Energy an Indian oil refiner. Now
this company NRA Energy uh it has a
certain amount of Russian ownership
minority stake. Okay. Uh and it's
importing Russian crude oil and refining
that and I don't know where it's being
exported but wherever. So the EU has
sanctioned it and then we hear the news
that Microsoft suddenly revoked access.
So Naira is a customer of Microsoft and
they have the data on Microsoft servers
or whatever it is. I don't know the
details but Microsoft unilaterally cut
off all access and they they restricted
Naira energy's access to the services
they have purchased
unilaterally now the sanctions were from
the U not from from the EU not from the
US and Microsoft is a company that's
legally bound to uh provide the services
that that have been paid for and that
yet they unilaterally cut that off for a
while and now it's been restored
apparently I'm not sure so what does it
mean was this mere tech technical action
absolutely not this was let's say a
trial run of what can be done in the
future right so look we depend on on on
platforms on services provided by the US
that overcomes the risk that is given to
us at their pleasure even if you pay for
it even then they can cut it off and
what what the hell can we do are you
going to go to the US and fire file
court cases
yeah even if you do that the US
government can intervene and have you
kicked out and have your court what
whatever they can do whatever they want.
Uh so this is the risk you run when you
don't have your own technological
platforms and your own technological uh
service providers. You don't have that
you're going to depend on outsiders.
You're going to depend on the superpower
and then they can control everything
that you do. Yeah. And you can't blame
them for that. Uh so what does it reveal
about the risks to India's critical
infrastructure? We are at their mercy.
We need to have our own operating
systems. We need to have our own
platforms. We need to have everything of
our own. And uh we're nowhere near that.
Terrible situation, right? Clearly.
Okay. So Khadka says, "Is MCC the
Millennium Millennium Challenge
Corporation a new way of the US to
vasalize countries be? Because it seems
like it's getting active in Nepal. Now
what are my thoughts about this
Millennium Challenge Corporation? It's
one of the innumerable US operations
that uh seek to vasalize various
countries. So you know
the Roman poet Virgil he wrote this poem
called the Iid.
It was about the Trojan warrior inas.
So Inas he was a survivor of the Trojan
war. He survived the fall of Troy and he
fled from Troy. He fled from Greece and
he traveled westwards and he ended up in
what is now called Italy.
So Anaas traveled to Italy, settled down
there and his descendants eventually
were Remis and Rmulus
and his descendants were eventually the
Romans. So Anaas the Greek warrior the
Trojan warrior who survived the fall of
Troy he was the ancestor it is believed
of the Romans. So Virgil this Roman poet
about
10 20 BC or whatever he wrote this poem
called the Inid which which is about in
his story and in this poem Virgil wrote
beware of Greeks
bearing gifts.
What's it mean? Beware of Greeks bearing
gifts. Obviously he's referring to the
horse, right? The Trojan horse. Beware
of Greeks bearing gifts. Today
we need to change that. Beware of
Americans bearing gifts.
That's all I'll say.
There's no free gift in the world. The
gift always has
always has uh an ulterior motive. Okay?
And if you are stupid enough as a
country to take these gifts in, it's
going to cause mayhem for you. It's
going to cause mayhem.
Mclivven says India did a great job in
operation Sindur. We doing great in
Europe selling weapons, oil, trade deals
and so on. We are also handling the
pressure of US tariffs so far, not
sanctions, tariffs. But why can't we
take care of the Manipur problem? We're
doing great globally, but our internal
problems are getting worse.
But like I said, like I said, this is a
project undertaken by the US. The US
sees India. Well, if India is allowed to
just grow the way it is growing
naturally, leave India alone, let it
grow. India in the next 20 years will
become the next China. Despite all the
problems India has, India has so many
internal problems.
Problems that are the consequences of
the decisions taken by various people in
in the 1940s. Those problems are legacy
problems. They still plague us. India is
still shackled by these colonial
problems and the legacy of colonalism.
The biggest problem we have is
corruption. Allegedly. Allegedly. Yeah.
And that there's so much inertia.
There's so much entropy within India.
Much of India's energy in incredible
vital energy is wasted within fighting
each other. Right? And despite all these
problems, India is still the the largest
the the fastest growing large economy.
And India could still become the next
China in 2030 years. And that will be
that will be a problem for the US. So
the US doesn't want India to ever be
that son of nation that ends up becoming
the next China and another headache for
them in the future. So best deal with
India now. And I don't blame the great
power, the existing hedgeim for behaving
that way. It is just the natural order
of things. If you are the hedgeim, you
don't want new future hedgemons to crop
up. You want to nip them in the bud.
That's just the way you behave. That's
how it is. Vishnu Chanaka would have
approved approved of that. Right? So
that's how it goes. But now we are here
and we are in the crosshairs.
So the ideal situation, the ideal
outcome
for the hedgeim is the bulcanization of
India. so many internal problems, so
many problems internally that we can't
fight outside forces and we just cave in
and give up, right? And ultimately we
get balconized or we we become a totally
different entity culturally and
religiously and and civilization no
civilization left. That's the ideal
outcome for them and that's why they're
pouring in possibly allegedly trillions
of dollars worth of funding into uh
large scale conversion activities in
India and other problems. So Pakistan an
artificial temporary nation is has
always been propped up by the US. The US
funded and financed Pakistani terrorism
against India for decades. We know that.
Now during the Biden administration
there was this new project that they
created new project project Kukiland for
Christ to create a new artificial
temporary nation east of India east of
the Indian far east. And this artificial
temporary nation would
would be a Christian nation and it will
be made created out of parts of Burma,
parts of Manipur, parts of M parts of
Miseram and parts of Bangladesh.
And who said this? The ursw prime
minister of Bangladesh said this while
she was still prime minister.
She made these allegations that there is
a project. The US is engaging in this
project and they're trying to balconize
uh Bangladesh and Myanmar and take parts
of Manipur and maybe the whole of
Bizaram and so on to create this new
artificial nation and the the purpose of
this new artificial nation is to serve
as an eastern Pakistan
and create the same problems for India
as Pakistan does on our western front.
Right? And the Manipur problem is an
outcome of that.
So why have has the west been spending
so much money Christianizing India? Why
have they we have our our former leaders
allowed them to Christianize much of the
far east. Nagaland is completely almost
completely Christianized. They have lost
their their traditional ancestral
culture. It's been wiped out. How
horrible. They are doing the same in
Arunachal. They they've done the same in
Mizoram, right? And now these foreigners
the cookies are being poured being
pushed into India and God knows how many
lakhs and half of Manipur is is overrun
more than half and the problem is just
persisting.
Now you may have heard that the
government of India is now pushing
beginning to take steps to push out
Bangladesh's Rohingyas to some extent.
But why is that not being done in
Manipur despite Manipur being right on
the border with Burma? Just push the
outsiders out right through the border.
it it can be done in in a few days. It
won't take years like the Bangladesh is
doing years. Why is it not being done?
Because this is a US project and uh the
moment you take any action in this,
they're going to start crying human
rights and you know do UN resolutions
and take all kinds of maybe impose
sanctions on India. Huge huge pain on
India if we try to solve the Manipur
problem. So that's the deal. India can
solve it tomorrow. one order from Delhi
and in three to seven days all
foreigners are out of Manipur. As simple
as that. In one way or the other they
can be deported on their feet or in
whichever way can be done. One order
from Delhi in less than 7 days the
problem is solved. But why are we unable
to do it? Because there is a foreign
hand and that foreign hand comes from
the largest power in the world and they
are so powerful that we are unable to do
it. We are unable to thus far solve the
problem. What is the Manipur problem?
There are you will have journalists
telling you that the Manipur problem is
there are multiple ethnicities in
Manipur who can't live together. That's
not the problem. The Manipur problem is
illegal foreign infiltration and and and
take over of Indian territory. That's
the problem. The solution to the Manipur
problem is to kick out all the
outsiders. As simple as that. It's not
about multi. It's not it's not some
civil war that's happening. It's an
invasion. An invasion is not a civil
war. So that needs to happen whenever it
happens. We'll see. See the
the foreign power is just too powerful.
It's so powerful China can't take back
Taiwan despite Taiwan being right at
China's doorstep.
People underestimate how powerful the US
is. Okay. China has always sought to
take Taiwan back. Taiwan lies at China's
doorstep and still Taiwan China can't do
that. That's how powerful the superpower
is. So what are we compared to even
China? China is about three and a half
four times more powerful than us and
they still can't do it. So can we solve
the problem? So these are pain points
being applied to India to destabilize
India and to keep India from reaching
its full potential. So do you see do you
see do you see these as friendly steps
by a friendly division against India?
No.
So understand what the manipul problem
really is.
Yeah.
Okay. Two questions about the same uh
essentially the same topic. Geopolitical
Dubai says uh the American president Mr.
Trump has announced that he will deploy
nuclear submarines near Russia or
whatever appropriate regions. Yeah. Is
this just a statement given out of
frustration or and anger or is he
seriously st taking steps? And Pra says,
"What's the real significance of Trump
publicly announcing this the movement of
two nuclear submarines near Russia? Is
this serious military signaling or
reckless political theater? Do
responsible nations ever declare such
actions so openly uh especially amid
nuclear tensions? How should the world
and India in particular read this
escalation as a credible shift or a
dangerous breakdown of or strategic
maturity?
So Trump was took offense to some
statements made by the former Russian
president Mr. Dimitri Midwev. Mr.
Dimitriv is pretty active on Twitter and
he is a he's got a very sarcastic snarky
tone. He's he tweets in very good
English and I think that has really
offended Mr. Trump. Yeah. Mr. Trump
seems to have taken it very very
personally and he has now publicly
announced that he is sending two
American nuclear submarines is deploying
them to the appropriate locations in
response to whatever Mr. Meduv has said.
Yeah. Now understand this American
nuclear submarines are on permanent
deployment across the world. Let's take
a look at the map.
Let's take a look at the map. Okay. US
nuclear submarines are they essentially
uh have unlimited range because they can
stay submerged for months on end. Uh
their legs the length of their legs
depends on how much food food they can
you know uh take
that uh on one mission. So typically 6
months they can stay uh submerged if
they need to and they have nuclear
propulsion which means they don't even
have to sub to surface for air. They can
recycle the air, the carbon dioxide back
into oxygen and and so on and they can
stay submerged for months. So their
missions can take can last months if
they need to. Now US nuclear submarines
are typically deployed all across the
world. At this point in time you will
have Indian US nuclear submarines in the
western Indian Ocean region the
so-called Arabian Sea region. You will
have nuclear submarines in the US in the
so-called Bay of Bengal, the Sea of
Kolinga. You will have them in the South
China Sea, the the Champa Sea. Actually,
you'll have them in the sea of Japan.
You will have them in the sea of most
likely you will have them in the bearing
sea. You will have them in the Arctic
Ocean region. And you will also have
them in the North Atlantic and wherever
else required. You will also sometimes
see US nuclear submarines crossing the
the the Sway canal. Okay, you'll see see
them sometimes. Um so the US nuclear
submarines are everywhere. They are
always on patrol. and they are an
integral component of the American
second strike capability.
So if he says that he is deploying two
nuclear submarines at appropriate
locations, what is he talking about?
They're always deployed.
US nuclear submarines are always forward
deployed. They're always in contested
waters, supposedly cons contested
waters. That's the deal about
submarines. They can be hidden and then
they go places where nobody else can go.
Surface vessels can't go there. So
what's he talking about?
So look, they they are already on
deployment. They're already deployed
wherever they can be deployed. And uh
he's just making a statement I would say
that you know he's he's kind of upset.
He's taken Mr. Medvev's statements a
little seriously, a little personally
and uh whatever. So yeah, he does have
as the president of the US authority to
deploy nuclear submarines wherever he
wants. You go deploy here, you go deploy
there, he can do that. But they're
always deployed. It's it's policy.
It's policy.
So what do I make of this? Is is this an
escalation? It's not an escalation.
Tensions are already high and whatever
assets need to be deployed wherever they
already deployed. You have nuclear
American nuclear weapons in Turkey aimed
at Russia. You have US nuclear weapons
in other U European countries aimed at
Russia. You have American nuclear
missiles on US territory aimed at every
other country major country in the world
including US.
you um and so on and so on so forth. So
that's standard nuclear posture.
Um so this is just an angry statement by
Mr. Trump. He's he is uh he has taken
Mr. Medv's statements a little
personally.
I don't see there's I don't imagine
there's any new deployment. They already
deployed wherever they can be deployed
there.
Okay.
All right. Miganga, Seeker, Biswas and
Prrenipal have the same question.
Essentially, Lat aerospace announced the
building of indigenous aircraft engines
and star successfully tested a hydrogen
oxygen powertrain. India is making bold
steps in strides in innovation. Are
these developments signals that we are
witnessing the the rise of India from
being a lowkilled assembler to high-end
engineering and designing? And Prne
says, "How do you view this bold
initiative by Zumat's founder and Lat to
build indigenous gas turbines, a space
India has struggled to conquer? And why
have IT giants like TCS Infosys despite
decades of global dominance never
ventured into deep tech or invested in
cutting edge national R&D the way LAT
now aspires to? What does this reveal
about India's tech priorities and its
future in strategic innovation?"
Okay. So it's Deepinder Goyel the
founder of Zumato
who is now venturing into uh the design
and development of gas turbine engines
something India has never done before.
India India struggled to do that. It's
great. I'm so happy to hear that
somebody who is who already has a
successful venture like Zumato is using
the proceeds and whatever the profits
possibly personal from that and using
that and in in channeling that into R&D
engineering R&D especially in a in a
sector like gas turbines which India
desperately needs. I'm I'm very pleased
to hear that. I think he should he needs
to be applauded for that. So now and
also star is apparently tested a
hydrogen oxygen power train. Now
somebody people will ask me what's a
power train? What is a power train?
Power train what is it? A powertrain is
the
is the mechanical apparatus that
that
connects the engine of let's say an
automobile let's say a car to its
wheels. So it transmits the revolutions
of the engine
and turn and and converts them into the
the motion of the wheels. That's the
power train essentially. It's this axle
and so on. Yeah. So that's a power
train. So hydrogen oxygen power train.
So you're essentially using hydrogen and
oxygen as the fuel instead of uh fossil
fuels. Yeah. Good, good, good progress.
And L aerospace is a bigger story. Uh
it's not announced the building of
indigenous aircraft engines. They're
starting the venture. I think deepind
the Mr. Goyel is looking for the right
kind of engineers. Yeah. So they're
right now assembling a team of engineers
and I think that their their their
philosophy is going to be that we will
do it as fast as possible. We'll test as
fast as as possible break things as if
need to fail as much as we need to and
then start making things happen. See how
do you develop something? Let's say you
want to build a new rocket new rocket
engine. I promise you the first time you
test something is going to explode or
fail or crash. Most likely it'll crash
on the launchpad itself. That's
necessary. Then you take the data of
what went wrong and then you improve
upon that. Then it may go maybe 3 ft up
and then explode. Okay, progress. It did
not explode on the launch pad. It
exploded 3 ft above. Then you take the
new data and you understand what
improvements you made worked and what
did not work. You make some changes. Now
that it'll go maybe 10 m up and then
crash. So you keep on iteratively imp
improving. Then one day you're going to
have it launch into orbit. That's how we
do it. You've got to break things.
You've got to fail lots of times. So the
the trick is to fail as quickly as
possible over and over again until you
start succeeding in small ways and then
you make the small ways bigger. So if
you want to develop something in
engineering, you got to fail lots of
times as fast as possible. You got to
break things first. You got to break
lots of things. So that's the philosophy
I believe that LAT aerospace is going to
employ. Right now they're looking at
building a team of uh talented people
and they don't care about what degrees
you have. They want to see if you can
actually do things which is great.
That's the approach we need to have in
this country if you want to make
progress. So it's great. So this is a
this is a something that's starting up
right now. We haven't yet they haven't
yet built any engines. Okay. But yeah, I
I applaud the initiative. That's what
needs to happen. More people who have
the funds and resources need to take
these risks, take these leaps of faith
and try and do something different,
right? It's good. It's great. So, we are
witnessing some kind of rise, some kind
of,
you know, a different approach in India.
We no longer doing the same old stuff.
Now what about TCS, Infosys, whoever
else you know their business model what
it was the entire Indian IT sector. How
many
how many new products has the Indian IT
sector created?
Have they created anything like
Facebook, like Twitter, like Instagram,
like uh Google, like uh OpenAI? Has have
has the Indian IT sector produced
anything new? They have produced a big
fat zero. The Indian IT sector they have
had
only one business model labor arbitrage.
So we have talented IT people in this
country lots and lots of computer
science graduates and whatever you know.
So they will take these youngsters give
you know train them a little bit
and then they will tell the American
companies look for you in the US if you
employ a programmer it's going to cost
you let's say $100 an hour we're going
to bill you $20 an hour
for the same work so obviously the
American companies will will contract
these Indian IT companies and then the
Indian IT companies who are being build
who are billing the the customer $20 an
hour. They'll pay the Indian uh
programmers a fraction of that. That's
called labor arbitrage. Everybody wins
except the poor guy who and the poor
girl who are programmers in India.
Yeah. Cyber coolies. So
way back I was a cyber once. So
I've seen the whole thing. It's it's
miserable. the the Indian IT companies
have no interest in creating anything
exciting or anything new. They just want
to mint money and now that model is
going to die. It's going to be a
disaster for India. But that's what it
is. They've never bothered. They've
never wanted to innovate.
They just being greedy about money. Show
me one innovation that's come out of
Indian IT companies. Nothing. It's that
mindset. Very bad mindset,
you know. So yeah it it tells you that
we don't have any visionary leaders in
the Indian IT sector. Nobody. So I'm
glad that Mr. Deepinder Goyel the
founder of Zumato is taking this risk
and I I wish him the greatest of
success. I'm very happy to see this.
Geopolitical Dubai says can we consider
ancient India to have been an otarchy?
That's a great question. That's a great
question. Ancient India. Let's talk
about India from a thousand years ago.
Our ancestors a thousand years ago and
the the same land that we live in a
thousand years ago. What was it like?
What was the lifestyle like?
We can't even imagine what our ancestors
were like a thousand years ago, right?
But forget about that the historical
part. But
was India at that time an utarchy?
What's an otarchy? That's the question
we to answer first. An utarchy is an
entity. Uh
a political or geopolitical entity which
is a country or a kingdom or an empire.
Okay? It's an entity. It's a kingdom or
empire that is completely
self-sufficient in all resources.
All energy needs are provided from for
within. All food security needs are
provided for from within. All resources
like metals and whatever else,
minerals, everything is available in the
country. You don't depend on any
external provider for anything at all
whatsoever. If you are in that
situation, you are an otarchy. You're
completely self-sufficient. You need
nothing from anybody else. Today, Russia
is an otarchy. The US, you can say, is
an utarchy. Yes. Who else? Nobody else.
So, was ancient India an utarchy? Yes,
we were in otarch.
See in the old days a thousand years ago
there nobody used fossil fuels. It was
all horsepower
and uh so we we had no dependence on
anybody else for energy and all the
minerals everything was available in
India. India is a gigantic piece of
territory.
we were completely self-sufficient when
it comes to uh food security,
agriculture, tremendous
um tremendously fertile land. So India,
ancient India was in absolutely no
turkey.
We were a net exporter of whatever
everything else, everything. The Romans
used to trade with us. They they used to
purchase our our spices and our textile
products and all that and they used to
in return they used to give us gold.
They used to sometimes complain about
it. that India is taking all over gold
because our people are are hooked are
addicted to Indian spices and products
and whatn not they in India most of them
anyhow so ancient India was absolutely
an utarchy so why are we not an
autoarchy today because we lack we have
we we are not self-sufficient in terms
of energy first of all right u we don't
have enough oil and gas resources that
we know of thus far that can provide for
all our energy needs that's the major
Achilles heel that we face today. That's
the major problem. Uh apart from that,
I'm what else? Uh I think we are
dependent on other countries for rare
earth minerals and various other things.
I think all of that can be solved.
All of that can be solved. We've just
our our our leaders, our governments in
the past have just been too lazy to look
for the resources within India. We need
to prospect.
Prospecting is hard work. But if we look
for the resources in in the gigantic
subcontinent, we'll find everything in
the sub in the subcontinent. So I think
it's a matter of time if we start
looking for us to find everything all
the resources we need. Even if it's
uranium, even if it's thorium, even if
it's oil, gas,
whatever rare earths, lithium,
everything will be available in India if
we just look for it. So we can become
anarchy again. But it'll it'll take some
time. It'll take some effort, some
resources, money, cash.
So yeah, you're right, sir. In ancient
India was absolutely not. Absolutely.
What next? Okay. Krishna uh Krishna of
Surinamese Netherlands says, "How long
will it take to correct the inaccuracies
and incorrect narratives in the
historical chronological timelines of
Parat Versa's history?
Okay, India's history is a mess.
Obviously, the written history today,
why is it a mess? Well, if you ask the
great westerners, they'll say that you
your history is a mess because your
ancestors never bothered to write
history. You were an ahistoric people.
You tended to memorize everything and
whatever you memorized was was stories
and myths, right? That's what they say.
The truth is this. We were not an
ahistoric person. Uh we were not an ah
historic culture or civilization. We
wrote everything.
We had universities
with gigantic libraries. All our history
was recorded and written down.
Everything was written down. And we lost
our sovereignty.
Foreigners came in. Turks, they
destroyed our universities, raised them
to the ground and burned our libraries.
Our libraries burned for months. That's
how big they were. And today any of the
old universities if you go there they're
all flattened they're all in ruins
they're all burned scorch marks
everywhere right? So we lost our written
history we lost the records of our
history that were maintained by our
ancestors. So what was left? We were
left with some memories and some tales
and those had to be passed on orally
because we could not build new libraries
and new universities as long as we were
under foreign occupation. They would not
allow us to do that. So we were forced
to pass everything on orally. And then
when the foreigners, the whites, the
Europeans arrived in India, they said
you are a people without history. You
pass on history orally.
Such primitive barbarians you are. So
let me do you a favor. You stupid
Indians. You stupid Hindus. I will write
your history for you.
Okay? And then they proceeded to write
our history for us. And then by 1830
they 35 or whatever that was officially
made part of the Indian education system
their version of our history and we
still teach that today that's the
problem. So now now that we understand
how it happened,
how long will it take to correct all
this, the inaccuracies, the incorrect
narratives and especially the historical
chronological timelines? The
chronological timelines will take time
because we have records of lineages of
kings. We have how many ancient
uh royal lineages? 36 I believe. I
believe there are there were
historically 36 royal lineages that went
back to the rigidic times. The royal
lineages of India. Uh who was it? James
Todd or somebody who who
collected that data and published it.
But it was known for obviously it was
known to us before that. Uh the 36 royal
lineages of India. And so we have
recorded lineages of Indian kings and
dynasties that go back thousands and
thousands of years. One example is
Kalhana the the Kashmiri chronicler. He
wrote the Raj Tarangini in which there
are records of kings that go back to the
Vic times. Okay. Mostly centered around
Kashmir obviously but obviously it'll
have the entirety of the Indian lineages
and we have other records here and
there. So we have to reconcile the
records and see sometimes some kings are
said in the records to have lived
several hundred years. What does it
really mean? Maybe it means their their
bunch or the lineage or the dynasty was
in power for for those many years. We
have to interpret it properly. So that's
going to take some brain power. You're
going to have to bring scholars
together. One person can't do it
possibly. Maybe we have to have a lot of
scholars come together and have maybe
our version of a solve conference for
history and then you know come up you
know understand what the what the and
decipher what the truth really is. So
this may be a long this may be long
effort. So the chronology
is is problematic. I'm pretty sure the
chronologies are mixed up are messed up.
I'm not even sure which Chundra Gupta it
was that faced u that that um there have
been multiple Chundra Guptas right in
Indian history which Chundra Gupta came
when which was the Morian Chundra Gupta
which were of the Chundra Guptas there
are lots of inconsistencies and there
are certain anchors that have been used
to to give dates to Indian history one
is the uh the the the
uh the attempted invasion by Alexander
the Greek and so on. But there there's
going to be lots of problems. We don't
even know for sure what's the date of
the Buddha. It is supposed to be uh
maybe the fifth century BC or
thereabouts. I'm not sure if that's the
absolutely accurate thing. So there's a
lot that needs to be looked into and
that's going to take a lot of time. It's
going to take a lot of brain power.
You'll need really smart people to do
that. But when it comes to the other
inaccuracies and incorrect narratives
that can be fixed, that can be solved in
maybe 2, three years. So all you have to
do is delegate the responsibility of
this to the to the states. How many
states do we have in India? 29 30
whatever the number is. So each state
has its own rich history that goes back
thousands of years. Right? So have let's
say each state government fund let's say
20 scholars in each state. Give them 1
cr rupees a year.
20 cr rupes is nothing. It's peanuts.
Give each scholar a a stipen of 1 cr
rupees a year. Have them work on one
aspect of the state's history and let
them collaborate in whichever way they
want. Get the brightest people hopefully
young people and give them a period of
three years let's say to do their
research and compile their work. So then
you have 20 volumes for each state and
those that can they can there can then
be combined into a proper full series uh
of history books for each state and you
can do it for each state in the country
right that will give you a complete
history of the country and each region
of the country in just 3 years. Then you
can digitize it and have make it
available to the entire population of
the country for free.
Obviously you to choose the people
correctly you know carefully and so it
can be done obviously so these
inaccuracies and all that stuff all of
this can be fixed actually resolved
pretty soon if there is political will
for it you need good leadership for that
um I'm not sure about that you know
whether the motivation exists or not
that's the problem
rightas
and Vladimir Putin says uh say now that
Nisar is in orbit with dual and SAR
what's a SAR synthetic synthetic
aperture radar synthetic aperture radar
uh offering centimeter accuracy surface
mapping every 12 days what strategic
value does it provide India in boosting
disaster resilience and infrastructure
moni monitoring and Mr. Putin Shri Putin
G says what are your views on the NISAR
satellite launch? How will it impact
India US relations? Uh how does it
impact Indian space technology? What is
NISAR? It's NASA ISRO synthetic aperture
radar. It's a satellite that recently
was put up into space. It was launched
from India. I think the Satish Davan
Space Center. It was launched using a
GSLV Mark III or whatever rocket rocket.
And uh it's probably the most powerful
um earth sensing remote sensing
satellite of all time possibly uh joint
mission between NASA and ISRO. Um NASA
has provided what? NASA has provided one
of the SS one of the synthetic aperture
radars I think the Lband possibly 1 to 2
GHz
frequency range and ISRO has provided
the Sband synthetic aperture radar which
is the 3 to 4 GHz frequency range or
something like that and ISRO also
provided the satellite bus and the and
the and the launch vehicle which is the
GSM rocket and uh yeah so that's it's a
joint venture joint uh project between
the two nations. Now the satellite is in
orbit. It's going to take a few months
to calibrate it and whatever else and
then it'll start operations. Right?
That's the deal. Now the question is
does it provide any strategic value to
India or the US or or what else? So
let's take a look. Let's let's Google
this, right? Let's see what NASA has to
say. Let's see what ISRO has to say
about this. I haven't looked into the
the satellite and its uh specifications
thus far. So let's discover it together.
NISAR
satellite.
What's this NISAR satellite? Um, let's
first go to NISAR on the NASA website.
Uh, NASA is synthetic aperture radar
designed to provide a detailed view of
the Earth to observe and measure some of
the planet's most complex processes.
Ecosystem disturbances, ice sheet
collapse, natural hazards, sea level
horizons, groundwater issues. Its radar,
the first of its kind in space, will
systematically map Earth. Measuring
changes over planet surface surface as
small as a centimeter. Fantastic. So the
mission partners are NASA and ISRO.
Instruments are two. Yeah. LSR and SR.
Yeah. Uh it's at an altitude of 747 km
inclination of 98.4°.
Um all of that. Fantastic. What do else
do we have? The magic of SAR. How the
SAR works. Okay, good. Very nice. How
the synthetic aperture radar works. What
data and so on. Okay, that's what NASA
has to say. Not a lot actually. Now
let's see what ISRO has to say about
this uh mission
mission MISAR NSAR designed to provide a
detailed view all the same stuff. Oh,
this is again NASA's website. Let's go
to ISRO's website. All right, here we
have it. Okay, NISAR is a first of its
kind mission jointly developed by the
two space agencies L and Sband global
microwave imaging mission with
capability to acquire full polar and
interpherometric data la. Okay. So, um
provides high resolution and large swath
imagery uh including islands every 12
days. Primary objectives are to study
land and ice deformation, land in
ecosystems, oceanic regions in areas of
common interest to the US and Indian
space communities. Measure the woody
biomass. Track changes in extent of
active crops. Understand changes in
wetlands extent. Map greenlands and
Antactica's arch ice sheets. Dynamics of
sea ice and mountain glaciers.
characterize land surface deformation
and seismicity volcanism landslides blah
blah blah and uh all that mainframe bus
imaging payload orbit suns synchronous
okay uh dawn to dusk kind of orbit very
nice u all of that nice mission phases
launch deployment commissioning science
so it's launched now it's it's being
deployed commissioning first 90 days
will be dedicated to commissioning in
orbit checkout and all that stuff and
then the science operations again.
So that's about it. Two-eyed NISAR
satellite, two, it's got two radars and
so on. Now, so that gives me some
information about what this thing is. So
does it provide any strategic value? No.
This is a scientific mission. It doesn't
provide any strategic value as far as we
know. Okay. Um
so yeah, as far as we can see from
whatever is being said officially in the
public domain, it doesn't have any
strategic purpose. It has a scientific
it has a scientific mission. Um
and it's about tracking natural
processes uh sea ice the ice caps uh
crops and wood surface you know wooded
area and all that stuff. Um disaster
resilience it may have some applications
uh infrastructure monitoring possibly.
So what a synthetic aperture radar does
is that it is that it allows you to
construct a two-dimensional
representation of three-dimensional
surfaces maybe a 3D representation
because you have two radars and there's
this Doppler shift effect that that uh
is at the heart of the synthetic
aperture radar physics. So yeah that
that sort of thing. So it doesn't really
provide any strategic value. This
particular satellite it does not uh will
it impact US India relations? It'll
impact it'll it'll be good for the the
uh the the the the cooperation between
the two scientific communities the
American scientific community and the
Indian scientific community. So Indian
scientists and American scientists will
collaborate on various research projects
and all that and share the data. It's
already a cooperation between NASA and
ISRO. So that's good. So overall it's
good from the perspective of the two
scientific communities. Um how does it
impact Indian space technology? Not
really. So it's a it's a successful GSV
launch which comes out for a while. So
that's good. Beyond that nothing nothing
much. Uh and it shows that India is has
got a robust uh set of technologies that
u that go into satellites. You know we
we have been manufacturing high quality
satellites for quite some time. So that
that showcases that um so it will not
impact India US relations at a
geopolitical level. It will be
beneficial for the relations at the
scientific level scientific communities
level. Beyond that I don't see too much
coming out of that.
Okay. Sharma 108x says between the
Iranian shakas excuse me Iranian shakas
because the west says that that the
skitians were Iranian.
Okay. Between the skitans the shakas the
tkarans the tushara people the koshans
and the turks. The history of central
Asia seems convoluted. What exactly is
the history of the Indian influence in
central Asia including the Tarin base in
Jungaria region and how did Shinjang
so-called Shinjang become a part of
China. Okay, let's go to the map.
Where's the map? Where's the map? Here
is the map. Okay. So, here is map. Yes.
And we have Central Asia all over here.
So, Central Asia you could say is is
east of Ukraine. Starts east of Ukraine.
uh it uh in my opinion from the way I
see it the ancient land called is today
central Asia soya also included present
day Ukraine actually but let's say it
starts from east of Ukraine which means
the cauasus region all the stans
Kazakhstanistan
turkmanistan tajakistan kystan and so on
so forth it also includes present day
so-called singang and all that excludes
Tibet so that in my opinion from the way
I see it is central Asia because that
was the region once called Skitia. It
was the land of the skitians, the Shaka
people. Now if you ask any western or
even if even if you ask Indian
historians, they will say that the
Skithians were an Iranian people,
irranic people. Now the question you're
asking is a very good question. So now
that we have established the geography,
let's
close the map. So now that we have
established the geography of Central
Asia which includes present day
Singinjang which includes the homeland
of this of the of the Kushana people
now that we understand that what's the
deal pretty convoluted it's convoluted
if you want to look at it see it's
complex or simple depending on what lens
you use to look at it if you use a short
lens if you look look at the the history
of the P of the region from the
perspective of the last 500 years only.
It's going to be super complicated.
Super complicated. If you look at it
from the perspective, if you examine the
history from the perspective of of the
last 1,000 years, it'll make a little
more little more sense. If you look at
the history from the perspective of the
last 2,000 years, it makes even more
sense. But the best way to look at it is
to look at it from the perspective of
the maybe the last 7 8,000 years. Then
everything falls into piece into into
place and everything makes sense.
So if it is complicated, it means you've
been using the wrong lens to look at
stuff. You've been looking at only a
certain time period. That is very
complicated. If you look at it like
that, you will you won't be able to make
out what's happening. It will be super
complicated. You will never get to the
bottom of anything. How did it all
begin?
You have to look at the origins
of the shakas, of the Persians, of the
tusharas,
everybody else. And we said the tokarans
and the kushans. Same thing. Same thing.
Where does it all begin, my friends? It
all begins with the earliest recorded
battle in human history.
Earliest recorded war
in human history. Earliest recorded
military campaign, geopolitical campaign
in human history. It's called the battle
of the 10 kings. Happened God knows
when. It's recorded in the oldest
literature in the world, the Rigveda.
So this battle happened and one it was a
battle between a confederation of more
than 10 kings and they were all a raid
lined up against one guy King Sudas
and it was an it was an rolling ongoing
conflict. It eventually culminated in a
battle between King Sudas and his forces
and on the other other side the 10 plus
kings altogether as a confederation and
King Sudas won
and those 10 plus kings were and their
people were expelled out of India. They
were ejected out of India.
They where did they go? They went
outwards northwest of India. Which land
which region did they go into? Well,
some they some of them went into what's
now called skitia or central Asia. Some
went eastwards. Oh, sorry, westwards.
Some went further west, somewhere less,
some went less less west.
So, the parro people ended up populating
Persia. Persia is named after the parro
people, Persians. The Alina people
became the Hellenic people. The helenic
the helenic people are the Greeks
and and so much more. Okay. So, Persia
was populated from
India. That's why there is so much
affinity between the ancient Persians
and the ancient Indians. Today, it's
different because of historical reasons.
But 2,000 years ago, the Persian people
and Indian people were essentially the
same. Very similar languages, very
similar culture, everything similar. Um,
so that is the Iranians, the Persians.
Who are the Skithians? They were the
people who lived in Central Asia, the
the the descendants of the the the the
people who fled, who were expelled out
of India, who were exiled from India,
the the end of the battle of the 10
kings. And they for for the longest
time, they were very Indian. When the
Skitians, when the Shakas reinvaded
India about 2,100 years ago, they were
able to assimilate very harmoniously
with the Indian population. Why? Because
they were the same people, same culture,
they were sun worshippers.
The language was also pretty similar
after all these years. So the skitians
were descendants of ancient Indians. The
Tushara people, the Tokarians,
well they are the eastern most skitians,
they spoke the Tushara language which is
supposedly a Satan language. But if you
look at the Tushar Tushar language which
I'll show you. Let's go to well let's
let's discover it for for ourselves live
live right now. Tokarian script we look
at the script but it will also tell us
tell us about about the language let's
go to omniglo.com
the Tokarian is an ancient extinct
branch of etc etc jantarim basin also
all that um so this is the tokaran
alphabet okay now what are the concerns
of the tokaran language ka
cha cha jana
ta da da da da da da
and so on. Doesn't it sound like exactly
like an Indian language? That's how it
was structured. The gods they worshiped
were the Indian gods
and so on. Their DNA, the male DNA is
mostly R1A. That's the HLO group mostly.
Not R1A, R1 A1A, RM17. That's that's
pure Indian. Yeah. And so much more. So
the Kushans, the Tusha, the Kushans were
essentially the descendants of the
Tushara people. to people um and so on.
So now I think the history of Central
Asia makes a little more sense. Later it
becomes convoluted because of the Tur
Turk invasions and all the mess that
that created. But for the longest time
you had Indian temples all across
Central Asia all across Central Asia. In
uh in Armenia
there were a bunch of Hindu temples that
were destroyed about 2,000 years ago and
churches were built on top of them.
Today those churches have been destroyed
by Azarbaijanis and mosques have been
built on top of those. That's the long
history. Even today you will see ruins
all across central Asia with Indian
deities. In Russia they find Vishnu
Vishnu statues of Lord Vishnu even today
once in a while there's Indian influence
everywhere. Everywhere but obviously
history won't historians won't write
about that right because no we don't
write about that. So yeah,
so that's I'll not go into Singinjang
becoming part of China and so on and so
forth. It's a long long stories, but
yeah, hopefully this explains about
Central Asia.
Um, okay. Reddi says, "My age is 25,
lost three UPSC attempts, wasted four
years in UPSC preparation, no job, no
respect from family and society.
Horrible situation every day. Feeling
like feeling like a loser and lost
everything. How to get give a solid
comeback in life to maintain how to
maintain consistency in life. I am I
have goals but I'm losing motivation and
consistency on a on regular intervals.
How to maintain cool calm composed
mindset like me and how do you how to
give solid strong comeback in life.
Please start raising your standard
series waiting for years. Yeah, I always
say raise your standards but I haven't
shown you how to right. You see you I
can't get you to raise your standards by
giving you lectures.
I can't do that. giving you a lecture
will motivate you for let's say half an
hour but once mot what is motivation
motivation is emotion right emotion yes
I'll do it but that emotion emotions are
variable emotions come and go you can't
rely on emotions to achieve goals I can
motivate you by giving you a speech but
after half an hour 1 hour that that
emotion will flow away right and you'll
come back face to face with the
realities of life
excuse me I can't motivate you or teach
you how to raise your standards by
giving you lectures or making videos or
or yeah essentially giving you speeches
and lectures. The only way I can do that
is by setting an example of some kind.
Yeah, that could be the raising your
standard series by by setting some kind
of example for you.
Yeah, maybe I maybe not maybe I'm going
to have to do that. So, how do you set
an example of how to turn your life
around? My life is decent now. I I no
longer have those big problems that
everybody goes through at some point in
their life. My life is okay.
But obviously there's so much to more to
achieve, right?
So the way to raise your standards is to
set big humongous goals and then create
systems for achieving those goals. You
can't rely on emotions.
You can't rely on what you call
motivation. You have to rely on systems
that you create. A system is is a
machine that can be used repeatedly over
and over again. It's it's a set of
processes that you follow
and you no longer have to rely on
motivation if you just know what is step
one, step two, step three and just do it
mechanically let's say every day and it
should be designed in such a way by you
that it will take you every day slightly
closer and closer to your goal. That's
how you do it.
So I can only uh help you or show you
how to raise your standards by by
actually creating that sort of thing and
implementing it in front of you in
public. Build in public like they say
maybe I'll have to do that very soon.
That's the way to do it. Now when it
comes to uh you you're 25 years old.
Yeah. You're 25. Your life is just
starting.
It's just the beginning of your life.
When you're 25, it means you've just
essentially come out of the education
system after wasting I don't know how
many years of your life. The real waste
of your life is the education system
where you learn nothing but you're
tortured every day and by the time
you're out you've gained no real skills.
Uh anyhow you're just starting off in
life. Yeah. Okay. You lost three UPSC
attempts, four years you wasted in UPS
preparation. Fine.
What you need to do is acquire some
skills and and become financially
independent. That's the first step.
Um,
and when it comes to family and society,
look, how how does society see a
person's worth?
How do you how does society decide how
much value a person has? Well, sadly,
it's all material value. They only look
at how much money you have. Essentially,
that's it. Or or whatever awards you may
have won or whatever. So my point is if
you want to gain respect from society,
from your family, family is also like
that. Fickle, it can be like that. Yeah.
If you are not successful, family also
might not treat you well. Unfortunately,
that's just life.
So you have to become financially
self-sufficient. You to stand up your
feet financially, become independent of
anybody else, and then you can start
building from there. How do you do that?
You acquire some skills whichever way. I
don't know your exact life
circumstances, so I can't tell you
specifically how to do it. You have to
acquire some skills that are valuable in
the job market. You to start with a job,
any job, become financially independent
and then take it from there.
25 is nothing. You're just starting off.
There's a huge amount of time left for
you in life. There's so much more you
can do. Listen, I know it may feel
terrible and so on. Yeah, you may feel
very low. You may feel very demotivated
and so on. But every great person has
gone through exactly that sort of
situation. different circumstances but
the same situation being very low. I
remember reading about Elon Musk. He was
on the verge of bankruptcy once. He had
to borrow money from his brothers,
sisters and family at one point in his
life which is very low right. Um so my
point is don't be don't give up don't be
demotivated. How to make a solid
comeback? You start from the very
basics. You start
by first becoming financially
independent by having a job. To have a
job, you will need skills that are
valuable in the job market. So you to
first spend some time acquiring those
skills.
Then gain some experience. Maybe you
have to gain some experience for 6
months by working for no money. Perhaps
the world is harsh. Pay whatever price
you have to pay. Get the experience.
Start with a small job. Uh become
financially independent and then work so
hard that you become rich. You know,
eventually you may even be able to
become independent of any job or
whatever. So it it depends. My main
point is don't give up. Don't be
demotivated. At 25, you are still very
young. You're just starting off. No
matter what anybody says, uh just be
positive and work as hard as possible,
right? All right, sir. All the best.
You'll do well. Do well.
Okay.
Now, let us uh take some questions from
the live chat. So, Aayush Singh has
advice. Marry a good girl and she'll
change your life. Listen Aayush uh
decent advice but the point is if you
are not financially self-sufficient no
good girl will marry you. Okay please
understand that
you have to provide some value to your
life partner.
So they will not see the value in you
until you are at least financially
independent. So one step at a time. So
yeah eventually once you have some money
and you're financially independent and
you have some prospects in life marry a
good girl very important if you have the
right partner well obviously your uh
life will change no question right
okay okay
um
so do ask some questions I am now in um
I'm looking at the live chat do we have
some interesting questions
Um
let us see let us see. Um anonymous
scientist says you can become a very
good motivational speaker. Well
motivational speaker well that's not
really something that really interests
me too much. Mo see
motivational speaking is very popular
isn't it? There are some people who have
made entire careers out of being
motivational speakers. And I'm sure it's
it's a it's a great niche on YouTube. I
suppose you could make millions by being
a motivational speaker, making putting
some epic music behind that. Epic music
and a wonderful motivating speech. But
that is snake oil. It will not change
anyone's life.
You can't succeed by listening to
motivational speeches. Sir, understand
that it is it is like fooling people. I
don't want to fool anybody.
The only way to succeed in life is to
create systems. your own systems for
yourself that will allow you to to climb
up the ladder towards success. A system
is a set of it's it's like a ritual a
set of rituals you perform every day in
a certain order. Morning I do this this
this then after that is done move on to
stage two. I do this this this then I do
that then that that. That's a system. It
has to be in a certain order in a
specific sequence a set of actions. Just
like a set of rituals you perform and
that's what takes you towards success.
Sometimes those rituals are difficult,
sometimes they're easy, sometimes they
are mundane and boring. Sometimes
they're very creative. Depends on what
you are trying to achieve. So that's
what you have to do. You have to create
your own systems. Nobody can teach you
how to create a system. I mean you I
suppose you could there must be books on
systems thinking and all. That's what
you need to look into instead of
listening to motivational speeches. So I
have I I suppose I could possibly be a
motivational speaker. I may be good at
that. I don't want to do that. I don't
want to mislead people.
So, yeah, there we have it. Next,
okay, let's see what else we have. Uh
um
Adita says if Chandra Gupta Mori were a
politician today, would how would he get
India to be a great country?
Um if Chandra Gupta Moria well if
Chandra Gupta Moria was a politician
today
how he would then have to be elected
and the best he could do was to be the
the highest achievement he could have
possibly
would be that he would become India's
prime minister.
If he was India's prime minister,
democratically elected, he would not
have the powers that he had when he was
emperor of India,
then he would be constrained by the
constitution, by the laws, by federalism
and all that nonsense. And it would be
very hard for him to make India a great
country.
So no politician will succeed in making
India a great country unless the system
is changed. So it will take somebody of
tremendous
force of will and fortitude to change
the system itself.
The current system is is designed to to
keep India mediocre.
And if Chandra Gupta Maria was alive
today then and if you're a politician
the best he can do is be prime minister
which is you know then he'll be
constrained by the system and he won't
be able to achieve the things he would
otherwise be able to achieve.
Um,
okay. Commando says, "My take on
extraterrestrial objects like three eye
atlas, um, Mua, Borisov, Ailib's
perspective." Okay. Um,u Mua is on its
way out of the solar system. It has a
it's an object that came very close to
the sun. I think in 2018 or somewhere
like 17 few years ago, it it came from
outside of the solar system at a very
tremendous high speed. It is on a
hyperbolic
path.
not parabolic but hyperbolic which takes
it out of the solar system. it'll go out
and never come back. And it came very
close to the sun and it seems to have
demonstrated certain characteristics and
behavior that that raise your eyebrows
like outgassing and acceleration while
going away from the sun and stuff like
that and extremely high reflectivity
almost like it's a solar sail or some
kind of things like that. And so I will
observe that it may have been an
extraterrestrial visitor. I mean a
rocket. I mean I don't know an
extraterrestrial spacecraft perhaps. Now
you have a new object that's coming
towards the solar system. Three Atlas.
It'll approach the sun closest to the
sun probably around October or something
like that this year. I haven't seen
looking into it thus far.
And even this object seems to have
certain strange characteristics. And
there's this paper out on the physics
archive archive.com
that says that this could be
extraterrestrial technology. It could be
an alien invasion. And if it is so then
so that sort of thing. What's my take? I
haven't really looked into the
characteristics of this object yet.
Umuama it's it's on its way out. So that
really is not a matter of concern
anymore from a security perspective. But
3II Atlas is coming towards the inner
solar system. It's going to it's it's on
a it's on a path that will take it close
to Jupiter then Mars. It's like an a
spacecraft on a tour of the solar system
which wants to visit all the important
planets. How close it is is it coming to
earth. No, not sure about that. But
yeah, so the they the authors, one of
whom is Ailib, they have raised the
concern that this could be an
extraterrestrial invasion, an alien
invasion and uh it could cause it could
it could it could pose a security threat
to us.
So
So what's my I think we'll have to look
into it. So I think we'll know by
October what the thing is. Just a few
months to go.
Uh Amisha says, "Do you see Raja Sultana
as a strong woman like Rani Lakshmi Bay?
When I was a small kid, you know, little
kid, Chutabacha, little toddler, this
movie came out, Hindi movie, Bollywood
movie, Razy Sultan." And uh Raza Sultan
was portrayed by Himalayan
and she had this slave guy whose name
was Yakul or something. He was portrayed
by Dhinder or Dhinder, very strong
apparently a African origin man. So in
that movie she's portrayed as a kind of
heroine kind of person very nice person
very strong and unjustly oppressed and
whatnot I a long time I remember the
scene in the desert and this this cobra
facing her or something I was a little
kid and some nice songs by what's her
name
so that movie portrays her as some great
great paragon of virtue or something but
the truth is that she was an oppressor
of Hindus oppressor of Indians so I
don't see her as a strong woman she was
a person who came and went she was never
really significant but she was a female
who who ruled for a while. What when did
she rule? She was the daughter of
Iltmish. Iltmish was the guy who hedged
all the bets when Shri Chingish Khan was
on the outskirts of India uh chasing
Jalaluduin the coward. Shir Ching Khan
about
yeah the battle of Indas he destroyed
Jalaludin's army on the outskirts on on
the on the western bank of the Indas on
the Siddhu river and Jalaludin the
coward jumped into the water leaving his
army behind leaving his family mother
everybody behind he crossed the water
and entered India and Shri Chingish Khan
said to hell with you go riddance I'll
not bother pursuing you because you're
done and he went back he went to deal
with China yeah Shir Jinghan
So the king in northern India, one of
the kings was Iltmish. He was a Turk. He
belonged to the slave dynasty or
something. The the the Mluk dynasty. So
Il Tutmish when he died for a while one
of his daughters called Raza was was
king for a bit for a while and then she
was deposed obviously and I believe her
tomb is somewhere in Delhi today in some
rundown part of Delhi. Was she a strong
woman like Marani Lakshmi? Nothing like
that. You can't compare Raza with
Lakshmi.
Lakshmi gave her life for our
civilization.
Raza was an oppressor.
She had nothing to do with our
civilization. She was not connected to
our civilization or culture in any way
whatsoever. So I I from my perspective I
see no comparison, no scope for
comparison whatsoever.
Right. Okay. Now um
let us see um
what's my favorite character from
Chabim? I have never had the misfortune
of watching Chota Beam. Um Chabim is I'm
sure lots of Indians have grown up
watching it.
H it's painful to watch
really the quality of the animation the
aesthetics everything it's terrible why
can't you make it better the concept is
good a character from Indian history
deep Indian history beam
I'm not sure what the story lines are
like I don't know what it is like but
the animation is so
unesthetic
and and I've just briefly seen some of
it it's just Yeah, I I it's not for me.
I've never seen it. I grew up watching
better cartoons, quality cartoons. I was
fortunate. Um, so yeah. No, no favorite
characters. Sorry. Um, okay. Maybe I can
take maybe one more question. One more
question.
Uh, of the modern Indian scientists, who
do you think are the greatest minds? I
can't think of anybody. Sorry.
Um,
yeah, I said one more question. I think
we're done then. Are we done? Okay, we
done sir. We done gentlemen, ladies,
gentlemen's, everybody, all of you. Uh,
so I'm going to end it over here and
tomorrow we're going to have one more
live stream. I will take super chats in
that so everybody gets to ask questions
and yeah, so I look forward to seeing
you there. All right, so as always,
please keep learning, keep raising your
standards, keep asking questions, and I
will see you tomorrow in tomorrow's live
stream. same time, 8:00 p.m. Indian
time, same channel. I look forward to
seeing you there. Thank you so much for
watching. Thank you for your viewership
and take care. Bye-bye.